[Music]
so
do
[Music]
done
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to the latest episode of ask a
budget today we talk about science
so let us see before we begin who all is
there with us i can see nirmit upanishad
prashanth prasad yash phoenix lucifer
akul
manish
and everybody else good evening good day
and welcome to this latest episode of
ask a budget
let us get into the questions and today
we are discussing science obviously so
what's question number one for today
question number one is by two people
vishal and sayan
is it true that in the future we're
going to use
small satellite launch vehicle and nano
satellite launch vehicle rather than
pslb and gslv how
would
sslb and nslv be more helpful
and what do you think of the recent ssl
sslv launch and its failure in the
terminal stage how is isro going to
benefit from a successful sslv
so the sslv is the small satellite
launch vehicle it's a new rocket that
isro has developed and it's uh well
strangely enough they've developed a new
small rocket
typically one would expect that when you
are developing new rockets you would
develop more powerful rockets bigger
rockets rockets that can launch a
greater payload into further and for
further orbits
but a slow isro seems to be going in the
opposite direction we are developing
smaller rockets apparently and uh
so uh what's the rationale behind
developing a smaller rocket a small
satellite launch vehicle i'm not sure if
there is an nslv in the in the works if
there is then okay
so why would one
build a smaller rocket develop a smaller
rocket it's like this you have the psl
with the polar satellite launch vehicle
in the gsl with the geostationary
satellite launch vehicle
these rockets are much more powerful
than the sslv so let's say you want to
launch a bunch of small satellites
nowadays we can launch multiple
satellites on a single rockets rocket
it's the same essentially the same
technology as mirb technology multiple
independently reusable
uh vehicles
right right there is there is a
ballistic missile in nuclear weapons but
uh it's essentially the same technology
so let's say you want to launch a bunch
of nano satellites one kilogram in in
mass
or maybe small satellites like
50 kilograms 100 kilograms each and you
will you want to launch three or five of
these
so the total payload is about
if it's uh small cycles it's about 500
kilos
what's the point
of launching a massive rocket
to carry a small payload
a single rocket launch when it comes to
the gslv or the pslv
would cost maybe tens of crores of
rupees maybe hundreds of crores obvious
the gslv is a much more massive rocket
so that
a launch of the gslv would cost much
more than a launch of the pslv
now if you want to launch the small
satellite you want a smaller rocket a
more efficient rocket and a rocket that
will cost less
right so as to optimize the costs for
per satellite essentially you want to
bring the cost per kilogram
as low as possible
and that is essentially the rationale
the reason
behind developing a new rocket that is
dedicated to launching small satellites
and possibly nano satellites right so
that is the reason why this has been
done it is a purely commercial thing
the reason is purely commercial ico
wants to
acquire a bigger share of the satellite
launch market
yes
isro will essentially serve as a taxi
driver
for
various clients
and launch their satellites into orbit
i'm not saying it in any kind of
derogatory fashion this is a viable
business model and yes why not make some
money right if you have the technology
for doing that
so uh lots of countries lots of private
companies worldwide need
a satellite
in position in space to to do various
tasks yeah
and therefore therefore there is there
is a growing market there's a growing
demand for launching small satellites
nowadays you have these cubesats nano
sats very small satellites that pack a
lot of electronics into a small volume
and they can do
whatever is required for a certain kind
of purpose right so these days you don't
have to launch massive bulky satellites
nations need to do that but but small
nations and small companies or large
companies don't need to launch massive
multi-ton satellites
so for that
it is it makes sense to develop a
smaller rocket
and that is what the sslv is the small
satellite launch vehicle and maybe an
nslv i'm not sure if that is also in the
works but yeah
so that is the reason why this has been
developed it doesn't mean that the pslv
is going to be shelved or the gslv is
going to be shelved when india starts
its human space space flight program you
can't do that with a small rocket
right you're gonna be launching a
capsule that contains that would carry
maybe three three astronauts yeah
that's uh that would
that's a large capsule that would uh its
weight would be significantly large
definitely
most likely over a ton
so you can't launch that sort of capsule
on a small satellite launch vehicle you
need
ideally the gslv for that so there are
various versions of the gslv also that
are in existence that have been
developed and there is still i believe a
work in progress yeah
so the gslv is not going to be shelved
neither is the pslv the sslv and the
nslv are for a certain kind of launch a
niche market that's all it is now what
do i think of the failure well typically
when you are developing a new new
technology there is a process of trial
and error uh the this uh launch that
happened recently was a developmental
launch that's how it's been uh
that's how it has been portrayed it was
a developmental launch
so when you see if you look at the
history
of the american space program or the
russian space program in the 1950s and
1960s you will see so many failures so
many rockets that failed to take off
that exploded on the launch pad or they
took off and they missed the target
completely
right initially the success rate was
about 20 or 30 percent the first few
years
right and then over time they figured
out what works and what doesn't work and
then they were able to improve the
performance of the rockets and that's
what happened so there's always a
process of trial and error so this
particular sslv launch did not perform
as
is planned
i think there was a problem the terminal
stage it was able to deploy the
satellites but they were deployed in an
incorrect orbit
and that's why they are not quite usable
that's what happened
so what will happen now is that they
will figure out what went wrong what is
the cause of this failure what are the
what exactly went wrong they will have
the data the telemetrics and all that
and they will identify
the problem areas and they will rectify
it
and i hope that this is tested again
soon not six months or 12 months in the
future the problem with isro i always
observe this it's because of a lack of
budget i i think
when something doesn't work well
they wait two three four years to try it
out again
talk about
the obvious example is chandrayaan ii
chandrayaan 1 worked well chandrayaan 2
was a partial success almost like 90
success the lander crashed on the
surface of the moon
i was hoping they would send a next
mission within six months
but we're still waiting for it this
thing happened in 2019 so it's
certainly due to a budgetary constraints
that's that's the that's the reason why
it takes so long for them to try it
again you give them enough money to see
when you have engineers
who are working on technology they want
to test it out rapidly
right
that's that's what makes sense if you
look at the way space x
uh operates they test things very
rapidly there are lots of
tests over a period of months
and even if you look at uh blue origin
they have conducted hundreds of tests of
various components of the rocket system
uh the
uh
and so on right the capsule that
contains the human beings that takes
them to space and all that they have
conducted hundreds of tests in the case
of isro it's one test in three four
years it's because of budget constraints
so it is it's okay it's fine to fail
but you've got to iteratively improve
upon what went wrong and you need to do
it rapidly
so i hope i would like to see the next
launch of the sslv within a couple of
months
and hopefully this time they rectify the
problem
i don't think that's going to happen in
the next two three months but that's how
it should be
so the only disappointment i feel is
that there is a budgetary constraint and
these the
engineers are not able
to uh
to test out new technologies as rapidly
as they would like to ideally i would
like to see a sslv launch once
in a in a month and after a few launches
you perfected the technology so you
launch once a month and you do it for
six months then you perfected the
technology but if you if you test once
in six months it's problematic and you
know the improvements are very small and
very slow so that is the only issue with
this otherwise there are a bunch of
brilliant scientists and engineers
so yeah that's about this
on the earth's ecosystem
what will happen if one day all the
cockroaches go extinct from the earth
are they important in the earth's
ecosystem
cockroaches yes cockroaches
coca rocha
so cockroaches are a species of um
insect yes insects there are various
species or subspecies of cockroach i
think there are different species there
is the chinese cockroach the american
cockroach the indian cockroach there are
small ones large ones different colors
dark colored ones light colored ones and
so on so forth yeah orange cockroaches i
believe and then
your standard
reddish brown cockroach and so on and so
forth very interesting uh
insect yeah
so what is the role in the earth's
ecosystem cockroaches
look every
species
that
inhabits the earth
has a certain role to play in the
ecosystem the ecosystem is essentially
in a way like a living organism it's it
exists in a state of equilibrium
homeostasis
so all the different species they
perform
specific roles in the ecosystem and it
is this combination of
millions of species performing various
rules that keeps the ecosystem in
balance so what about cockroaches what
do they do
cockroaches are reasonably abundant
in the world they seem to like living
with human beings right so it's always a
problem for people who don't keep their
residences very clean or whatever or
sometimes even if you keep it clean
they're still around right cockroaches
so the thing is this
cockroach is
first of all they serve as prey
for other species of animals or insects
uh i've seen cats hunting cockroaches
and eating them with great relish meow
meow yeah cats like cockroaches
apparently
and
other species of of maybe birds etc
would also prey on cockroaches and eat
them
so the cockroaches are a good
source of nutrition
for many other species
of
of rodents of mammals
cats birds etc they're a good source of
nutrition a good source of protein for
these species
secondly uh cockroaches uh
they they what they do is they eat
organic material
and they accelerate the decomposition
process of this organic material
so when
there is a piece of food let's say a
piece of bread lying on the floor or or
somewhere else cockroaches would go and
eat that and and
decompose it rapidly to simpler organic
material that can then go back into the
earth and and enrich the
the
fertility of the soil and all that you
know so these are the kind of rules that
an insect like a cockroach would play
and i'm sure they also prey on other
smaller insects so that's they they
serve as prey and they also
serve as predators so there's always
this sort of balance you know big fish
eating small fish that sort of thing
so i am not an expert in cockroaches but
that's the general answer i can give you
this applies to all species of insects
animals birds
fish etc
on the planet they serve multiple
purposes and uh
and what if cockroaches went extinct so
if you were to suddenly snap your
fingers and make them all extinct there
would be a sudden imbalance in the
ecosystem and that would persist for i
don't know years decades possibly when
the the role they were fulfilling
cockroaches or fulfilling in the
ecosystem suddenly disappears there's a
big hole and then the ecosystem would
have to rebalance itself and
yeah there would be some consequences
maybe there will be an explosion of
certain kind of insect species that were
being preyed upon by cockroaches and
maybe there will be an extinction
possibly of certain
animal species or insect species that
primarily dependent depended on
cockroaches for food so there could be
that sort of imbalance
yeah so i think
all species have their own significance
and importance in the overall ecosystem
of the earth and if you make any any
species extinct there's gonna be a
certain imbalance yeah
so
in evolution species go extinct all the
time new species emerge all the time but
it happens over long time periods
so there is no sudden impact on the
environment but if cockroaches were to
go extinct one day like you say that
would cause
a
an inequilibrium
you know in the environment and that
would be problematic so that could cause
such consequences like i just mentioned
so that in brief is about
cockroaches
shaheen wahman zadigan says what is ball
lightning
yeah it's it's a very poorly understood
phenomenon ball lightning
so this
some people say it's it's superstition
or something but it's definitely not so
uh people have reported these phenomena
for centuries for millennia
and uh recently they have even been
caught on cctv camera etc so what is
this it's it's a ball of light
maybe it's it's a ball of glowing gas
possibly or maybe it's an electrical
phenomenon it's typically 10 to 20
centimeters in diameter maybe somewhat
sometimes it's larger in even rarer
cases
and it glows it pulsates and it wanders
around
at approximately human head height yeah
not always but sometimes and it wanders
around at walking pace
and sometimes it it disappears in an
explosive discharge sometimes it just
fizzles out so let's take a look at what
this actually looks like let me let me
try and put that on the screen
ball lightning
let's see what that looks like
i'm sure there are images of that
available
let's look at ball lightning let's do a
google search
so what does ball lightning look like
let's see some so so these are
certain
they've taken i mean some of these
phenomena have been captured essentially
on cctv mostly in cctv cameras
it's not always ball like but this this
one here as you can see looks like a
ball
there you are
something that looks like this sometimes
it's uh
sometimes it's high in the sky
sometimes it's a lightning strike that
creates this ball like thing yeah
there's another example so this is
typically what ball lightening looks
like it comes in various shapes and
sizes in various colors sometimes it's
reddish sometimes it's yellowish
sometimes it's bluish
those seem to be the most common colors
for bald lightning
uh yeah it's not very well understood it
certainly is something that exists it is
not
it's not a myth
yeah it's been captured multiple times
on stage cameras but it seems to be an
extremely rare phenomenon
and when something is so rare it's
really difficult to replicate that in in
you know as an experimental physicist
so if you don't know how something
happens you don't know how to replicate
it
and if you don't know how to replicate
it you don't you don't quite get to
understand or figure out what is the
physics behind that right what causes
this phenomenon so that is the reason
why this phenomenon is extremely poorly
understood it's not been replicated as
far as i know in any lab
and there are various hypotheses as to
why this happens maybe it's a it's a
glowing discharge of electricity of some
kind or maybe it is a glowing uh
gas
that uh
sometimes what happens is in marshy
environments you have natural emission
of gases from decomposition of
of various organic substances under
water and you have the emission of gases
like methane etc and these are flammable
gases so sometimes it could happen that
that causes this sort of phenomenon
possibly that's one hypothesis that's
one theory
and there could be uh electromagnetic
effects also possibly behind this so we
don't we're not quite sure but that in
brief is what ball lightning is it's a
very poorly understood phenomenon but
it's a phenomenon that definitely does
happen
swapnil says what caused the planets in
the solar system to orbit the sun in an
anti-clockwise manner and not clockwise
how would the earth have been different
if its revolution around the clock
around the sun
was clockwise
look what do we mean by clockwise or
anti-clockwise it all depends on where
we are
if i if i have a clock here
in front of my face over here yeah
it's going in a clockwise fashion but if
i was on the other side it would seem to
go in an anti-clockwise fashion
right
so when you have a solar a stellar
system with a star in planets
typically all the planets revolve in a
certain direction if you see it from one
orientation they will seem to be
clockwise if you see it from the other
orientation on the other side of the
disk they will seem to be anti-clockwise
so whether it's clockwise or
anti-clockwise depends on where you are
looking at looking at the place the
thing from that's it that's what it is
right
so uh there's no way of saying what is
the orientation is it clockwise it is it
anticlockwise
it doesn't matter
if you see it from above
let's say above
if there is there is no up or down in
space first of all so if you if
so let me show you what a stellar disk
looks like one second
um
let's see what this is so uh let me put
that on the screen
here we are
so the solar system
formed for something that looks like
this a proto stellar or pluto proto
planetary disk
so this
happened so so where did all this gas
come from
this gas that
eventually formed the sun and the
planets it came from the deaths of a
previous star a star that existed in
this region previously
and it most likely went supernova it
exploded in the end stage of its life
and the gas
was present and eventually it again
coalesced
there are various star-forming regions
in various galaxies where you have a lot
of gas and that accretes together and
eventually forms this sort of thing
so the thing about gravity
is that when you have a gravitating mass
of let's say gas it will have a center
of gravity where
that's the center of gravity right at
the very center of this uh of this
object or this region
and when you have a center of gravity
all the other particles of gas and dust
and whatever else will be attracted
towards that
but the velocities will be such that the
direction of the of the
motion
of these gas molecules of the trap will
not be directly uh towards the center
of the center of gravity of the mass and
that is what causes the rotational
motion right the entire
proto planetary or protocellular disc
will have a rotational motion
and that is what gives rise to the re
the the fact that planets orbit
around their their parent star and that
is also what causes the rotation
of planets
so that is what happens and
they will the planets will orbit around
the sun or the star and if you look at
it from one one direction they will seem
to be doing it clockwise if you see it
from the other direction they seem to be
doing it anticlockwise
so i don't know
whether the
earth is orbiting the sun clockwise or
anti-clockwise it is doing it both ways
depending on where you're looking so
that is the answer
okay rtk says why is there such a huge
difference between humans and the
species closest to humans
what led to the rapid increment of the
personality of homo sapiens
well i can certainly tell you agree that
homo sapiens has a wonderful personality
we all have incredibly great
personalities i mean look at our
closest relatives
chimpanzees gorillas langurs orangutans
their personalities aren't that great
compared to ours i mean we can do things
that they can't
but on the other hand they can do things
that we can't
the only difference between us and them
essentially is the level of intelligence
we have gone way beyond them but if you
look at the dna
then the dna the difference in dna
between me
and a chimpanzee let's say
would be about one percent or maximum
two percent somewhere between one and
two percent
so the difference in the genetics is
actually quite minimal
minimal
and yet it is that one or two percent
difference in the genetics in the in the
genetic code
that
makes us so different right
but are we really that different from
our closest uh
relatives the chimpanzees the gorillas
orangutans and bonobos etc
we
morphologically we are quite similar
we are not as
powerfully built or physically strong as
them
we are quite weak and puny
but morphologically we are very similar
to monkeys
apes
especially yes
uh
so i would not
quite know if we have such a huge
difference between us and them
even if you look at various other
species or families of species let's say
you look at the cats
you have your regular standard issue
house cat you know the domestic cat that
lives with humans
and
then you have other species of cats
you have the karakal
you have the links you have the puma and
then you have larger cats like the
jaguar or the leopard or the cheetah or
the lion or the tiger and so on and you
have various other extinct species of
cats like the saber tooth tiger and all
that
i'm sure there is a significant amount
of one or two percent like
difference in the genetic code in all
these various species of cats and yet
they have so much difference
morphologically physically especially
from the size perspective
they look quite similar if you were to
take a standard issue house cat cat and
magnify it by a factor of 10 it would
look very similar to a tiger
it's built and designed the same way
it's just that there are certain genetic
changes that have caused its size
to be what it is
so it's all because of the
game of evolution
species diverge from time to time
so the the last divergence between us
and our closest relative the chimpanzee
happened about
2 million years before today that's 20
what is 2 million that's 20 lakh right
20 lakh in indian terms yeah
so about 2 million years ago
our species diverged from that of the of
the our closest relatives of chimpanzees
and because of various reasons we're not
quite sure what the reasons are maybe
the formation of the rift valley people
have postulated that could be the reason
uh maybe two population groups became
isolated from each other because of
various reasons and they never were able
to intermingle for millions of for like
more than a million years
and that's why the
divergence of species happened and then
when you are living in different
environments you evolve differently so
that is how it happens that is how the
divergence of species happens uh about
six or so million years before today
the common ancestor of humans and
chimpanzees diverged from the common
ancestor of humans chimpanzees and
gorillas
and even even then there is a great deal
of similarity between us humans
and our gorilla relatives they are also
quite
similar to us in a variety of ways they
are like massively
muscular versions of humans right
and so on but they look quite similar to
us in in a variety of ways
so it is all because of
uh
evolution
you live in different environments
you're gonna evolve differently you have
to adapt to the environment and it's
sometimes
a
question of random mutations that happen
in dna but only those that are
beneficial
survive long term because of natural
selection and so on so that is what
happened that is how it happens i would
not say that there was a rapid increment
in the personality of homo sapiens i am
sure that our magnificent personalities
developed over about two million years
and in the future maybe we will be even
better but right now i think our
personalities are reasonably good
okay shubha says is the metaverse really
going to be developed further or is it a
concept with a lot of loopholes
we just spoke about evolution
evolution happens in technology as well
in business as well
technology
evolves because of financial
considerations
especially in a capitalist world such as
the world we live in
right
so companies
corporations develop technology with the
singular purpose of enriching themselves
they want to make money
they want to make their shareholders
money and they want to make their
essentially the shareholders right
the shareholders are the people who own
stakes in the company share the company
and the more the the company makes money
the the more the richer the shareholders
become so that is the primary purpose
and how do you do that
how do you
make your shareholders rich
by providing a certain kind of value to
the public the public
needs something or wants something or
has a certain problem
and you provide solutions to that
and then the public will give you money
in written for that that's how you make
money in any business
and sometimes you create solutions to
problems that don't exist
or maybe sometimes you create things
that that addict your customers or hook
them into this dopamine release
cycle
right
you you hook them to pleasurable things
drug dealers do that they sell drugs to
their customers and the customers get
hooked to that they get addicted and
they need more and more of that and you
can charge a lot of money for drugs
similarly certain technologies like
certain technologies could be like that
i'm not saying all are like that but
some some could be like that
so um
what is this meta was the metaverse is
going to be it's it's kind of
somewhat here
but not quite
in the future what you're gonna have
is all surfaces
will be will be
uh
all surfaces around you let's say walls
would be like laptop screens
you'd be able to watch a movie on your
wall on demand
and there would be elements of augmented
reality you wear glasses
and through those glasses you will see
metadata all around you so you're
walking on the street wearing glasses
and every single person that comes in
front of you
you will see certain data for that
person this person's name is this born
on so and so date this is their
financial value right now and so on so
forth depending on the level of access
that you have so if you are a government
agent
working for the government with a
certain level of clearance you will see
their entire life history
displayed in brief
and that could help you identify
suspects or whatever
similarly you could play virtual rail or
augmented reality games like the pikachu
thing that was a big craze it's gonna be
taken to the next level eventually so
right now what's happening is that the
virtual reality headsets or augmented
reality headsets are quite bulky right
in the future
the technology will be developed further
maybe in the next five to ten years
maximum and
you will have your regular glasses that
will give you the same effect in the
future you may not even need glasses you
may have contact lenses that would do
the same thing and
further down the line you'll have brain
implants that will give you
pleasure on demand or augmented reality
on demand and so on so forth so that is
the metaverse it's going to add
layers of of reality
on top of the actual reality we live in
right
and the hope
for these companies these are all
american companies that are doing this
yeah they hope that uh the entire world
will be hooked into this they wish to
create entirely virtual worlds and
universes for people to inhabit
um
you already have such environments
there's this game called roblox it's a
platform on which
there are like
a billion plus users mostly kids
teenagers and even even younger kids who
spend hours every day playing the game
and there are various other environment
environments as well the hope is that
you will be able to bring these into the
real world
and merge the two things so virtual
reality reality in actual reality will
be merged
and
it will also have some actual benefits
like you'll be able to learn things
faster you may be able to sit at home
and yet be in school or sit at home in
your bedroom and actually be
at the same time in your office in the
company of your colleagues and so on and
so forth
this is going to happen there is a
significant massive push
you know
to make this a reality and there's a lot
of money in that if you are a company
that offers your customers this sort of
thing then yeah you're going to make a
lot of money for sure and that's why
facebook has renamed itself to meta
and
so it's a bunch of american companies
silicon valley based companies that are
trying to change the entire reality that
we all live in right and it's going to
end up benefiting them it's going to end
up benefiting the customers and the
demographic they are targeting is the
youngsters
the generation z the zoomers
and even even younger kids
that's whom they want to hook into this
because in in 10 years
gen z kids will be young adults
and if you have hooked them into this at
the young age then they will be your
lifelong customers and there's a lot of
money you can make out of each other
each of them
so that's the kind of thing it is
i don't know what
loopholes it has but yes there are
drawbacks
uh
it is it is not all going to be great
for us
you could have kids
sitting on a mattress in a dark bedroom
no lights and they are wearing a headset
augmented reality or virtual reality
health headset and they imagine they are
super heroes and they're doing
conquering the world and all that in
reality they're sitting in a dark corner
of a dark room on a mattress with no
physical activity just hooked into this
uh virtual pleasurable universe and it's
not good for anybody for this or
something to happen but yes
that is something that
we are going down that alley right now
it's not all good for us technology
is always a double-edged sword you can
use it for good you can use it for bad
you can use fire to do good things you
can use fire to do bad things you can
use sticks and stones to good to do good
things
and bad things you can use nuclear
power to go to do good things for
humanity and you can also destroy
humanity with it similarly all these
technologies also have dual use multiple
users and
generally if you want to make a lot of
money you sometimes
lead people down the wrong
road
and that's how it works yeah
so that is the deal with the metaverse
i'm not sure it's all good for humanity
and
it could also
end up
transgressing on national security
national borders all that because the
internet doesn't know any borders yeah
and so if you are a company that
essentially is the platform for the
whole world you can set the rules and
you can disregard
the
laws and norms that are in place in
various countries you decide what it's
going to be like and everybody has to
obey you so these are problems that are
going to emerge
and
the
the nations that control this technology
are going to essentially rule the world
so that is the crossroads that we are at
right now that is what the metaverse is
it's it's not one thing you can
in the past they use the term cyberspace
today we have replaced that with the
term metaverse it's essentially the same
thing it is essentially the same thing
it's just the next level of cyberspace
more and more immersive
then you will have metawars 2.0 3.0
maybe by 2050 or something in which you
will be completely immersed in these uh
in these
virtual environments so that is what the
metaverse is
okay the i'm not sure what the name is i
can't read that but uh the question is
the potsdam institute for climate impact
research in a recent study
suggested that the combined effects of
natural and man-made emissions-based
global warming can delay the next ice
age by a hundred thousand years
whereas other celestial phenomena change
in orbit extra tilt precision etc will
continue as before obviously uh the
average interstitial glacial period is
about 10 to 11 000 years and we are
nearing the end of this period what will
be the possible changes that the earth
encounters next
okay good question so there are a number
of factors
that
cause the cycle of ice ages you have
like you said the the the change it's
not the change in orbit it's the
eccentricity of the orbit which kind of
changes over time yeah
it's a cyclical thing
then you have the axial tilt that also
changes the earth is the axis of the
rotation of the earth is tilted
compared to the plane of the solar
system there's a tilt this tilt also
changes
that that takes several thousand years
the axial tilt and then you have the
rate of precession so the precession
happens and
there also has an effect on
the climate of the earth so if you take
these various factors into account you
have what is called the milk cardinal
witch cycles
so
there was this scientist called
milkanovitch that's the name i remember
i don't know the first name so he i
think it was a he
so he calculated that uh
i think it was 41 000 years so according
to his calculations there should be an
ice age every 41 000 years or the cycle
should last 41 000 years
and that apparently indeed was
was detected to be correct but then
there was a problem of the hundred
thousand year cycle like you were
mentioning here so that is the hundred
thousand year issue or problem or
something they call it so instead of
forty one thousand years it's it's a
cycle of about a hundred thousand years
and like you mentioned the interstitial
glacial period means the
the time period between ice ages is
about 10 to 11 to 12 000 years and we
are nearing the end of that which means
that maybe in a few centuries maybe in a
thousand or two thousand years this
could be we could be entering a new ice
age or we should be about to enter a new
ice age and yet now we have this issue
of global warming yes
and that's what the question is about
so i have not seen this uh
study that you're mentioning but
we certainly know that there is
this issue of
man-made emissions
the
carbon that is being released into the
atmosphere into the environment right
and that is at i believe a significant
high right now and that is causing the
greenhouse effect the global warming and
by the end of the century
it is believed that the average
temperatures on the planet will rise by
about two degrees maybe three degrees i
hope not three but definitely two
degrees which is a significant increase
right
so what is going to be the effect of
that on the
global
100 000 years cycle
um
we don't quite know see the uh
climate is a very complex
thing there are
maybe millions of parameters that
go into
creating the weather that we are
experiencing right now
millions of parameters and you no matter
how powerful your super computer is you
cannot factor in
all of these
parameters
so like you said you have the major
parameters like the orbit the
eccentricity of the orbit the axial till
the precession of the equinoxes those
things
that is there
then you then you have the greenhouse
gas emissions that are going to warm the
planet by about two degrees by the end
of the century so typically an ice age i
believe
decreases
the overall average temperature of the
planet planet by
between 7 to 10 degrees
so if the average temperature say don't
quote me on that i may be somewhat off
yeah but it decreases the temperature
significantly that's why you have ice
sheets
all across the world
so if the average temperature where to
hypothetically let for the sake of the
argument drop by 10 degrees but you have
this warming which is caused by human uh
by by
by man-made emissions which will
increase the temperature by two then a
simplistic
approach to this would be that
you would have a decrease in temperature
not by 10 degrees but by 8 degrees
so the ice age would still occur but
maybe it would not be that severe as it
would otherwise have been
so there have been certain disruptive
uh
phenomena in the past
that would otherwise not happen for
instance the last time something strange
happened was the
something catastrophic happened was the
uh chick-fil-a impact which happened 66
million years ago
which was a very massive impact which
killed off the non-avian dinosaurs
it led to a condition similar to a
nuclear winter for about a decade or so
there was no uh
sunlight so it was not a greenhouse
thing it was the opposite of that
uh so we're not sure if it had any
long-term consequences
on the climate of the planet
i don't think there are any leftover
effects of that catastrophe
on the climate
today so that was obviously 66 million
years ago but over a period of a million
or two million years there would
definitely have been a significant
cooling of the earth even after sunlight
uh reappeared on the planet
so um
so there will definitely be some impact
but we are not quite sure i don't think
any scientist has been able to predict
exactly what the effect of man-made
global uh man-made emissions in the
global warming is going to be like
if the ice age is due to happen it will
certainly happen maybe it will not be as
severe as it would otherwise have been
but it would still happen
so the two degrees rise in temperature
would not be able to completely offset
the 10 degrees decrease
degrees decrease in temperature that
would be the result of an ice age so
maybe the ice age would be somewhat
milder but it would still be there as
far as i understand
so that's how i see things going
swarup says if light has no mass why is
it affected by black holes
online says kimcho
do light rays radio waves x-rays etc
kinds of waves
way do they have weight they have mass
and what type of substance are they made
of
uh so light rays light waves whatever
x-rays radios these are all
electromagnetic radiation so what are
they made of they're made of pure energy
a light rail let's say we call it a
right light ray or a radio wave or an
x-ray whatever you call it these are
nothing but photons photons are packets
or bundles of pure energy that have a
certain frequency and a certain
wavelength the frequency is one upon the
wavelength the wavelength is one upon
the frequency
so they aren't made of made up of any
substance they're made up of pure energy
initially the universe was just pure
energy at the moment of the big the
so-called big bang
it was
all the mass and energy of the entire
universe compressed into a single
point a singularity so it was all pure
energy and then eventually
it the space time expanded and
things happened like things happen
and that gave rise to all the mass that
we see we see today because of the
various things that happen
later on
so x-rays light rays radio waves gamma
rays all these things they are just
electromagnetic radiation it's pure
energy it has a certain wavelength in a
certain frequency
now
the other question is if light has no
mass why is it affected by black holes i
think i've answered this
more than once but let's take it again
so
light
doesn't have mass light has energy
but we now know
because of uh
albert einstein who first showed us this
that energy and mass are interchangeable
energy is equivalent to a certain amount
of mass and mass is equivalent to a
certain amount of energy and it's the
most famous equation most likely in
physics e equals m c squared
is the energy m c squared m is mass and
c is the speed of light
so energy
is equal to
m mass times the square of the speed of
light that's how you
translate energy into mass and mass into
energy equivalence
so
light
has energy the equation for the energy
of a photon is e equals h nu or hf where
h is the frequency
of the of the light
so depending on that and h is the uh
planck constant
so um that's why
even though a photon doesn't have mass
it has an equivalent mass or an inertial
mass so to say or a relativistic mass
you can
you can give it any name you want
inertial mass or relativistic mass but
it does have an equivalent mass to its
energy
now why
is light affected by black holes well
from the perspective of general
relativity
we live in a four dimensional space time
right
and mass the presence of mass in
space-time
has the effect of curving
the four-dimensional fabric of
space-time
so it's the it's it's what you the it's
a good old trope right you have a flat
surface a trampoline kind of surface you
put a ball in that and it curves the
surface right that sort of thing so
space-time is curved not only the three
dimension of dimension of space but also
the fourth dimension of time it's curved
by the presence of mass mass tells space
time how to curve
and the curvature
of space time tells mass how to move
right and since
space time gets curved light is not able
to travel in state straight lines and
that's why it travels in a curved
path and that is why light is affected
not just by black holes but by any kind
of mass
so that is one way of looking at it the
other way of looking at it is that light
even though it has only energy it has an
equivalent mass and that's why
it is affected by
black holes and other massive objects
that's another way of looking at it
it's just analogies that i'm giving you
but i hope that helps you understand why
this phenomenon happens
paulo me says
could you please tell us why do
fireflies glow in the night and if they
fly the whole night around why when do
they sleep do insects sleep
why do fireflies glow in the night uh
you know what fireflies can glow in the
day as well but you don't see it
so uh this is called bioluminescence
uh
fireflies have a certain enzyme
in their abdomens
i think it's called luciferase or
something like that
and when this
enzyme
reacts with oxygen it produces light and
it's cold light so when you have a light
bulb
it in order to emit light it also has to
has to become hot so that is
there is hot light
any light bulb will become hot when it
glows similarly if you heat a piece of
metal it will glow but it will also emit
a lot of heat
in the case of fireflies this reaction
that happens this bioluminescent
reaction is cold light so it does not
release any heat if it were to do that
it would kill the fireplace
so uh it is a chemical reaction
this enzyme
that reacts with oxygen
causes the glow to happen and the
fireflies can control the glow
when it starts when it stops and
typically they do it in pulses you know
and if you see a whole forest full of
firefights you will find even fire you
will find they are blinking in unison in
synchronicity yeah
so that's what you observe that's a
whole different phenomenon so why do
fireflies glow because they glow because
of a phenomenon called bioluminescence i
think it's a enzyme called luciferase if
i'm not mistaken
that is behind this
fireflies don't have lungs they don't
breathe but they do absorb oxygen
through variety through a variety of
means
and they can control this this entire
process which is why they are able to
control the vedic glow so the glow
impulses on off on off on off
now uh
do fireflies fly the whole night i don't
think they fly the whole night
typically they're sitting on branches
and leaves and all that and they're
glowing and doing things
um what is the purpose of the glow i'm
not sure what the purpose is maybe it is
to attract their mates may maybe it is
to
communicate with each other maybe it's
to warn away
predators saying that i am not good to
eat this enzyme which glows is not a
doesn't have a good taste and it will
upset your digestive system or something
like that so we're not quite sure why
they glow but they do glow i don't think
they fly the whole night
in my experience they sit on branches
and leaves and they sit and
and blink that's what they do
uh do insects sleep
insects do sleep
uh
insects
have a central nervous system
and it is something that we observe in
all
animals
that have a central nervous system that
they need sleep
right
so it is a property that seems to be
inherent to all creatures that have a
central nervous system a brain
and a nervous network a network of
nerves and neurons and all that that
that is present throughout the body
but typically you need to have a brain a
brain is essentially a biological neural
network
so
any animal that has this sort of central
nervous system
is observed to sleep sleep has been
observed in flies you can see that if
you if a fly is sleeping their response
to external stimuli is is delayed it is
slow if you deprive flies flies of sleep
then they need to catch up on more sleep
just like human beings
so yes insects do sleep not just
fireflies but i think all insects
need
a period of sleep
per their whatever circadian cycle they
have which is the typical 24 hour cycle
that all
humans and other animals
that we observe they have such a cycle
so yes insects do indeed sleep
anita asks three questions
can nukes help us fight an alien
invasion
is it true that drdo has more
non-scientific employees than scientific
ones
and why is there no factorial of
negative numbers all right let's see
this
can nukes help us fight against an alien
invasion
i think that if aliens have the
technology
to traverse interstellar space many
light years
and reach the earth
if they have that sort of technology
which is way more advanced than anything
we have then i don't think nuclear
weapons are going to be a big deal for
them
uh
so
i am a little skeptical
first of all we don't know if aliens
exist
we have never found any evidence thus
far maybe it's because we are too
primitive when our detection mechanism
is not good enough but if aliens do
exist and if they're able to come all
the way here and try to invade us then
it means that their technology is way
way way more advanced than anything we
can imagine
and if it is that advanced then i don't
think nuclear weapons are going to make
a
big dent on their efforts to
to uh invade us like you say
invasion
so it's like you know
a fly or a mosquito trying to bite you
you can just swat it off that sort of
thing it may have this that sort of
effect for
aliens
so uh if aliens can come here and try to
invade us i am a little skeptical if
nuclear weapons could deter them or or
defeat them yeah
okay is it true that drdo has more known
scientific employees than scientific
ones as far as i know drdo has roughly
30 000 employees on its payroll
and about 5 000 of these employees are
scientific staff scientists or engineers
which means that about 25 000
of the 30 000 employees are
non-scientific staff
i don't know what what function what
purpose they serve what function they
perform
but it's seeing it's it looks like a
colossal waste of money
a massively colossal waste of money let
me see if i can find something online
let me see
okay
what do we have all right i have a
wikipedia so as always please be
informed please be warned that wikipedia
is not necessarily a reliable source i'm
just putting it for the sake of
convenience and brevity i'm sure there
are sources here
so if you see this it says that it has
30 000 employees out of which 5 000 are
scientists
and it gives some reference
let's take a look at the reference if
you're able to open it
maybe it's not openable
let us see
so yeah it does look like it has only
5 000 scientific employees out of a sum
total of 30 000 employees so just
imagine
the kind of salaries
you're paying
30 000 25 000 non-scientist employees
you have to pay their salaries because
they're government employees you also
have to pay their pensions whenever they
get retirement and all that it's a
colossal waste of resources in my
opinion
the document did not open maybe we'll
take a look at it at the time some other
time or maybe you can do some of your
own research about this but yes it is
indeed the case
that
there are way more non-scientific
employees in drdo than scientists
why is there no factorial of negative
numbers
so how do you define a factorial let's
say you have five the number five
the factorial of number 5 is defined as
times 5 minus 1 times 5 minus 2 times 5
minus 3 all the way to 1.
it's 5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
the factorial of 10 is 10
times 10 minus 1 10 minus 2 and all all
the way up to 1
right
so it is that is the way factorials are
defined there is no definition
of the factorial for negative numbers
let because if you try to do the same
thing for a negative number let's say
you want to do 3 factor minus 3
factorial
then you would have to do
minus 3 minus 1 times -2 and so it would
go all the way to minus infinity
so uh it's not something that is
definable or defined for negative
numbers
factorial essentially is a way of
arranging things
let's say you've got five different
cards or five different chairs in how
many different ways can you arrange them
that is the meaning of factorial
yeah so in the case of negative numbers
there is no way of arranging negative
numbers because negative numbers are
actually in the real world unphysical
or or they are something that that only
exists in in
mathematics not in the real world
because there is no minus one in the
real world right
so uh these are the reasons why there is
no the factorial for negative numbers
has is not defined
so that's
what i could explain or i can explain
aditya ranjan saaho says please throw
light on the super cameo
kamyo khande project and its purpose
working etc uh when will india start
investing amounts into particle
accelerators joint voltages like lhc et
cetera okay let's talk about super
camiocande
uh the super comic on the uh detector is
a neutrino detector
it is
in japan
it is located deep deep deep underground
in in a disused mine of sorts
so let me show you what it looks like
i'm sure we can find an image of super
kamikandi
all right let me put that on the screen
and show you this thing in all its glory
give me a second
let us
place that on the screen
so this is what the detector looks like
from inside
these bright things that you see are
called photo multiplier tubes
and the detector
is filled
with ultra pure water
which means that this is
it's going to be filled with water that
has almost no impurities whatsoever the
water that we regularly use and drink
and all that it has full of is full of
impurities
dissolved minerals
salts other chemicals other things as
well in very small quantities but it's
all still there i mean when you drink
mineral water it has minerals dissolved
into it
so this water that is
used in this detector is ultra pure
water
almost 100 purity
and
like i said all these bright things
are
um
photo multiplier tubes so what happens
what are neutrinos neutrinos are are
fundamental particles that are that are
emitted by the sun
every single second
trillions
of solar neutrinos
are passing through my body every single
second and through your bodies as well
the sun gives off incredible amounts of
solar neutrinos per second
neutrinos have incredibly small masses
they're all they they
it was believed for the longest time
that neutrinos are massless but now it
is known that neutrinos have incredibly
small masses
close to zero very close to zero so the
sun emits through its nuclear reactions
trillions
incredible amounts of solar neutrinos
and
trillions of them pass through our
bodies every second
the neutrinos interact weakly they
interact only through the weak nuclear
force which is
which is incredibly incredibly weak
so a neutrino
can pass through the earth without
interacting with a single atom
inside the entire earth
and trillions of such neutrinos pass
through the earth so what this
experiment does
what this apparatus does is that it has
ultra pure water in this tank and the
tank is surrounded by all these uh
these detectors yes
and
we know that there are so many nutrients
passing through this water in this
chamber and every once in a while
one of these neutrinos will interact
with one of the molecules of the water
in here
and the interaction is going to be such
that uh
it's going to produce a flash of light
and this flash of light is going to
travel
faster than the speed of light inside
water but but slower than the speed of
light in vacuum
and this gives rise to what is called
the cherenkov effect
and these photo multiplier tubes are
going to
their purpose is to detect these flashes
of light which happen just once in a
while maybe once a day or so
even though there are so many neutrons
going through this
detector
so that is what this apparatus does and
through the detections it's able
it is able to study the properties of
neutrinos so that is what this detector
is the supercar you can they
detect a neutrino detector
and
it can help us detect supernovas because
when
a star explodes in a supernova explosion
it releases incredible amounts of
neutrinos
and
that can help us
understand
supernovas better
so and it can also help us detect
where these super nodes are happening
and so on and so forth so there are
multiple reasons why this
detector has been constructed and that's
what it is about
so the next question is when will india
start investing money into particle
accelerators joint ventures like
electric etc i don't think that's going
to happen
uh
we have a couple of detectors somewhere
or the other
in the tifr in mumbai there is this
there is an ancient uh
ancient instrument called a peletron
which uh
which accelerates i believe lead ions to
a certain velocity and all that and
collides them with targets and you can
do some basic nuclear physics
experiments with that i think it's been
around for decades yeah this electron i
believe
and
we may have some other
instrumentation as well but nothing
nothing cutting edge nothing
which would be considered to be the
latest kind of thing you know
so particle accelerators cost a lot of
money
it's a it's a very advanced technology
and for instance the large hadron
collider
i believe it cost billions of dollars
maybe around 10 billion dollars maybe
more roughly something like that that's
a lot of money
and it consumes an enormous amount of
electricity in its operation
so i think the budget of the lhc was
larger than the annual budget of many
countries
so it's very expensive and there is no
point constructing a particle detector
that is like underpowered because you're
not going to do any new physics with
that you're not going to make any new
discoveries with that
so uh
so there is no point as such
right now of constructing
a next super expensive
particle accelerator in india right now
because whatever had to be done whatever
experimentation
needed to be done to discover whatever
we discovered this far has already been
done in other countries
so it would be like reinventing the
wheel and what's the purpose of that
yeah
what is going to happen is that india is
going to get its own ligo so ligo is the
gravitational wave detector that
has done all the detection of
gravitational waves thus far
when was the first gravitational wave
detected i think it was in 2015
or thereabouts yes
that was done by ligo so india is going
to get one lego detector
it's going to be called indigo or
something uh the project was approved
several years ago i don't know what is
the status of the thing right now you
need a big bunch big piece of land on
which you build the detector it's in um
it's a michaelson interferometer kind of
design
it's each arm is several kilometers long
so what india will be getting is
essentially the same
detector as the two detectors in the us
and eventually
maybe in the next five years or so five
or ten years or so it will become
operational i don't know why it's taking
so long but yeah that's how it is in
india everything takes a lot of time
so that is one thing that's going to
happen in india
that is the kind of experimental physics
that will
be done here but apart from that nothing
else
that's how it is
summerth says how do wildfires begin
what is a wildfire season is it complete
completely because of climate change
a wild fire is a forest fire or or a
fire that that takes place that occurs
in uni inhabited land
typically
a forest or a jungle
or or grassland savannah that sort of
thing yeah
how do wildfires begin and what's the
wildfire season
see
i believe that about most of the
wildfires that begin are are because of
man-made
causes
about 15 or 20 of wildfires would have
natural causes
maybe 80 of them roughly
are
initiated by by man-made causes
somebody is smoking
and they dump their cigarette butt
somewhere without without extinguishing
it properly
that may
and and
that may cause a wildfire
or or somebody sets a small fire just
for for arson purposes that could cause
a wildfire you have an electrical short
circuit somewhere that could trigger
a fire in a forest or or what's called a
wildfire so most of these wildfires
actually are caused by human beings what
are the natural causes of wildfires so
typically a wildfire a forest fire takes
place in the dry season when there is a
drought or when there is a summer the
heat is high that's typically when
these fires occur
fire needs three things first of all it
needs fuel so let's say dry grass or a
dry forest where there is very little
moisture
so it needs fuel firstly secondly it
needs oxygen
we have oxygen everywhere and thirdly it
needs a spark a temperature
that ignites the fire
so typically
it is lightning
that sets off natural wildfires
when you have a lightning strike on a
tree and if the tree is dry then that
naturally causes a fire and then this
fight the fire can spread if the forest
or this this area is dry
so that is typically how wildfires begin
through natural causes what is a wild
fire season typically it's a summer
season or a season
a period of time
when you have dry weather there's no
rainfall so forests are dry grassland is
dry and that makes it very conducive to
start burning if there is a fire
if you have
a forest that has recently had rainfall
even in so in such a forest even though
if there's a lightning strike
that fire will most likely not spread
far it may just burn down the tree but
the surrounding trees and grassland will
not be affected much because they're all
wet
when you have drought or or dry season
that's when the fire can spread
so that is what a wild fire season is it
is a dry season let's say in australia
yeah
so in recent years
in 2020 i believe 2021 as well you had
these massive
this massive spate of wildfire outbreaks
and it caused a lot of damage many
animals died because of that because of
that many people lost their houses
you've had wildfires in spain in europe
as well
and i believe in
1998 or 88 what was it or 86 i'm not
sure which year it was there was this
massive wildfire season in the
yellowstone national park in the us
i think it was in the 1980s or 1990s
maybe 1990s and a significant
proportion
of this national park was burned down
in these this outbreak of wildfires and
even a decade later you could see the
burned down trees they were still strewn
around yeah
so uh that's how it happens and
often what happens
is that firefighters and
national park wardens etc they are
overzealous
in combating wildfires
fires often happen about 10 20 of fires
happen due to natural causes by
lightning strikes and so on
such fires should not be hindered
this is a natural phenomenon
such fire should be allowed
to go on and die off naturally
so when you allow that to happen when
you have allow these small fires to
progress and die natural deaths
that ensure that there are patches of
forest land or dry land that are cleared
out naturally
if you don't
allow natural wildfires to to die a
natural death
then over time your forest
becomes
a
ticking time bomb and when a fire does
happen almost the entire forest will be
burned down
so that's why sometimes these people
they get overzealous in combating and
stopping wildfires
uh so yeah that's that's what it is is
it completely because of climate change
i don't think it's completely because
because of climate change but yes we
have extreme weather nowadays you have
hotter summers
in in recent years so that does
contribute to a certain degree
to the
incidence of wildfires and the intensity
and severity of the effect
yeah
okay karan says
what is
what are cosmic rays and what is cosmic
wind
okay cosmic rays are essentially
fragments of atoms that come from space
from outer space and they bombard the
earth typically you have fragments of
atoms as in
atomic nuclei
so what is the nucleus of a hydrogen
atom it's a proton
what's the nucleus of a helium atom it's
an alpha particle
and so on
so typically
then you also have electrons and all
that so cosmic rays
are
the this bombardment of atomic fragments
that happens from outer space it hits
our atmosphere
and it it causes downstream effects so
typically when
a cosmic ray
hits the atmosphere it in it interacts
with the atoms in the atmosphere the
upper atmosphere
and
a new kind of article is created out of
this it's called pions
yeah
pions are created and pioneers decay
into muons and muons are what hit the
hit the earth and they go deep into the
earth's
crust into the earth's surface
so that is typically what cosmic rays
are now cosmic rays come in a variety of
energies
uh most cosmic rays are reasonably low
energy cosmic rays like like a small
underpowered
particle accelerator
but you also have these
very energetic cosmic rays ultra high
energy cosmic rays uh ecrs
that
are more that have more energy than
anything the lhc can produce for
instance
right
so yes you have these cosmic rays once
in a while uh ecs ultra high energy
cosmic rays that you find
i think in the 1990s one there was a
cosmic ray detection that was called the
oh my god particle
it was
i believe a proton or some such fragment
of an atom
but the energy is it the energy it
carried was like a cricket ball
traveling at around 60 kilometers or 100
kilometers per hour
that's the kind of energy a single
atomic fragment was carrying
it was called the oh my god particle
yeah
so that's what cosmic rays are it's a
natural phenomenon if you go higher into
the atmosphere you find a higher
incidence
you find you are able to detect more and
more ionized
atmospheric uh
particles and so on yeah so i think
these cosmic rays were detected in the
1910s or 1920s
by a scientist by a physicist who went
up into the atmosphere on a balloon
and measured
the amount of ionization of the air at
higher altitudes and that's when
it was detected that it was discovered
that there is higher ionization as you
go higher up into the atmosphere and
that was the discovery of cosmic rays
so that's what cosmic rays are
now they are not quite sure of how they
are produced there are various
possible mechanisms one mechanism is
that it is they are produced by
supernova explosions
uh
active galactic nuclei
various other uh mechanisms are also
proposed
there are more exotic mechanisms that
have been proposed like the annihilation
of dark matter particles
hawking radiation
things like that so we're not quite sure
of exactly how cosmic rays are produced
especially the ultra high energy cosmic
rays but various mechanisms have been
proposed and some of them have been kind
of corroborated like there is
there seems to be definitely a supernova
component
to cosmic rays so some cosmic rays are
definitely produced by supernova
explosions but why do cosmic rays
come in all the time
most of the cosmic rays are
deflected by the earth's magnetic field
but some of them definitely uh hit the
atmosphere and the effect can be
measured yeah
so that's what cosmic rays are what is
cosmic wind it's
it's the very thin diffuse amount of
dust and gas that you find
in interstellar space
so let's say you're in a rocket or a
spacecraft that is traveling across the
stars in interest
interstellar space space is vacuum
but it's not a perfect vacuum there is
there you'll you will encounter some
atoms
of hydrogen
and some other elements from time to
time it's a very very very thin and
diffuse gas but in some parts
of the cosmos you will have thicker dust
clouds
thicker gas clouds especially in star
forming regions and so on in nebulae etc
so all of this is what makes up cosmic
wind it's what you encounter as you
travel through interstellar space that
is cosmic wind
pawn says
please talk about the permian extinction
and how cyanodonts were able to survive
in those conditions
is it true
that we are successors of cynodonts
so you're talking about the permian
triassic extinction event event that
happened roughly
[Music]
250 million years before today maybe 251
million years before today you can look
up the exact
time period when this happened but
roughly
250 million years before today 25 crore
years before today it was one of the
uh most severe
extinction events
that we have
uh witnessed in the history of our
planet
i think uh
more than 60 or 70 percent of species
terrestrial species went extinct
and maybe maybe close to 90 percent of
marine species may have gone extinct
during this extinction event
so that's what the permian triassic
extinction event was what caused this
we're not quite sure of what caused it
it happened so long ago and the evidence
for this extinction event is found only
in the fossil record
so you can see that lots lots of uh
animals have died out and the fossil
record is found in sedimentary fashion
in sediments and you can see so each
sediment that comes above the previous
one is a is of is a subsequent time
period it represents a subsequent time
period you can see there is this
sudden change in the fossil record lots
of species that are found below have
suddenly disappeared which is the sign
of an extinction event
so we know this happened because of the
fossil record but we are not quite sure
why it happened
typically it's a combination of multiple
factors
one of the factors that is possible
is a massive super volcanic explosion in
siberia the siberian traps it was called
so that could have contributed to
this extinction event we also know that
the oceans had become anoxic
what is anoxia
it means
the oceans
lost their dissolved oxygen
how do fish
breathe how do fish survive they need
oxygen they need oxygen in their blood
so there is
oxygen that is dissolved in the water of
the oceans and rivers and ponds and
lakes etc
which the fish use for respiration
through their gills
if the ocean becomes deprived of water
if the if the level of
oxygen sorry if the level of oxygen that
is dissolved in the water decreases
beyond a certain level you will have a
massive
dying out of marine life
first of all the fish will die if the
fish die then those the animals that eat
the fish will also die so that will
cause a cascading chain reaction
and if it if the anoxia is widespread
then it could cause an extinction event
like the one we are talking about
so it is known it is
most likely known
that the waters the oceans had become
anoxic in large parts
and water had also become acidic
apparently
because of various reasons so you had a
combination of factors you had the
anoxia in the oceans you had
acidification of the oceans and you had
the siberian traps super volcano
explosion eruption which also
contributed to this so maybe it's a
country
a combination of these factors that
caused the permian triassic extinction
event about 250 million years before
today
now
you are asking me about cyanodance let
me show you what cyanobonds look like
so cyanogens were the ancestors of
mammals
this is what cynodons looked like they
they lived during this period
and uh
there were many species of these
creatures cyanobonds
that looked kind of like dogs kind of
like rats yeah that's what they look
like they came in different sizes and
shapes
and uh yes so these were the ancestors
of mammals
one of the lineages
of these cyanobonds
survived
and that is why we are alive today
so these creatures so these animals that
you are seeing here are artistic
recreations
of what these creatures would have
looked like and
these are our ancestors
so yes all mammals that that survive
today are the descendants of one lineage
of cynodonts that was able to survive
the triassic permian extinction event
so how did cynodont survive this we
don't know
maybe it was a species of small
synod that survived if you are small you
don't need a lot of food
you don't need to consume large amounts
of food if you are a small creature
and maybe that's why they were able to
make it similarly
their descendants that survived the
uh
the chichalub impact event also survived
most likely because they were small
so there was this period of nuclear
winter after the
impact
and
we know that our ancestors the mammals
of that time survived maybe it's because
they were small and similarly the avian
dinosaurs also survived because they
were small in size and they were able to
survive on on less food
so typically typically if you are small
in size it actually kind of
in these adverse conditions
helps you to survive
larger species of animals die out very
easily because they need large amounts
of food to survive
so that's
how it works so most likely
cynodons or the lineage of cyanogens
that survived survived because of a
small size
okay karan says the ultra massive black
hole 10 618 is 2606
astronomical units in diameter
while our entire solar system is 80
astronomical units in diameter the size
of this black hole is mind-boggling
how would such a large black hole form
um
what is an astronomical unit first of
all
an astronomical unit is the distance
between the sun the sun and the earth
that distance the average distance
between the earth is called one
astronomical unit
so i'm not sure how
large
the diameter of the solar system is
the actual solar system if you if you
consider the wood cloud and all that
extends to beyond one light year in
diameter
but yeah if you consider the the
main planets up to
neptune maybe a pluto maybe if you look
at the other outer
planet uh minor planets etc maybe it's
80 astronomical units
and
if we take that as the diameter of our
solar system then this this supermassive
black hole is monstrous and massive
let's see
what it looks like
so we don't
have an actual image of the black hole
but we have
these artistic
representations of this thing
so yeah you can see that it's it's quite
large let's see
a comparison if you can find
between this thing and the sun
all right so so yeah there you are so
it's an enormous enormous black hole the
question is
how did this black hole become so large
so large
um
okay so how do black holes form there
are multiple mechanisms
through which black holes
are born
uh the most well-known mechanism is the
death of a star if a star is a certain
size maybe 20 solar masses or more
then it
at the end of its life it goes supernova
and there's an implosion
and the implosion
the mass
in the implosion
that is falling inwards is so much it is
so high that it
it
collapses into a black hole right it it
is able to overcome the other forces
that are
trying to prevent the collapse
the pauli exclusion principle and all
that and it collapses into a black hole
that is one mechanism of black hole
formation
now
what we know
is that most galaxies
have a super massive black hole at the
center
our own galaxy the milky way
is known to have a super massive black
hole at its center
and
all the other most of the other galaxies
that we know
know of
have super massive black holes at their
centers
so
it is one of the theories is that
galaxies
formed in the early universe around
black hole seeds
black holes that eventually became
supermassive black holes and maybe this
supermassive black holes originated as
primordial microscopic black holes so in
the very early universe it is
possible
that an incredible amount of
microscopic black holes were formed
because of quantum fluctuations
and because of the incredible densities
that we had in
energy densities that we had in the in
the early epoch of the universe
so you would have regions of over
densities that would collapse into into
black holes and these are the primordial
black holes we have never detected any
but
according to the laws of physics
it is quite likely that enormous amounts
of primordial black holes may have
formed so when you talk about
a black hole this large
incredibly large larger than the solar
system itself
most likely such black holes
would form from the merger of multiple
smaller black holes
so the merger of a black hole is like
you could you could
consider the analogy of two
water drops merging that sort of thing
yeah
so a black hole this large we don't
quite know how it is formed but most
likely i would imagine it would have
emerged out of multiple mergers
of multiple supermassive black holes
and that would have happened in i don't
know in the past 13.8 million
billion years somewhere
so what are the exact circumstances that
led to its formation we still don't know
and maybe we may never know because it's
i don't know how far away it is from
here
but yeah
one of the scenarios is the merger of
multiple black holes maybe it swallowed
entire galaxies and the supermassive
black holes that came with those
galaxies
and there is one possibility
so
we don't have the answers but there are
multiple scenarios that could
lead to the formation of a black hole
this size
nagasai says
how do living organisms know
at what rate they should age time
dilation
depending on the gravity
general relativity or velocity special
relativity that they experience
okay so aging
and general relativity or special
relativity
see listen organisms don't know anything
organisms age as part of a natural
biological process
i am an organism we are all organisms
if we would have our way we would never
age at all
yeah
but it doesn't work like that it's not a
question of what we want
and
what we
wish to do
and what we know
it's just a biological process physics
is not involved in this
of course
it is quantum physics that gives rise to
chemistry and it is chemistry that gives
rise to biology so yeah the the deepest
level it is quantum physics yeah sure
uh but really relativity doesn't seem to
enter the picture so there is no time
dilation here there is no
special general relativity involved in
the aging process
of animals and organisms
so how does aging happen
in the body in any body in any organism
you have cellular division
yeah cells divide and that's how they
reproduce and that's how the the body
produces new cells
now
most cells
carry dna
our red blood cells don't have nuclei
and they don't have dna but most other
cells have dna
and the dna comes
is found in the nucleus of cells in the
form of chromosomes
right
now these chromosomes come come in
various sizes and shapes x chromosomes y
chromosomes these are the
um
these are the sex chromosomes then you
have other chromosomes as well there are
23 pairs of chromosomes in the human
in the humans in the human cell as far
as i remember yeah
now when cell division happens the
chromosomes also divide and they
replicate
each time cellular division happens
the ends of the chromosomes which are
called telomeres become slightly shorter
let's see what a telomere looks like
let me put telomeres on the screen
so telomeres are these structures at the
ends of chromosomes
every time
cellular division takes place
the telomeres at the end of the end of
the chromosomes become slightly slightly
shorter
and as you grow older as your body ages
there is more and more cellular division
that takes place at a certain rate
and over time
the ends of your chromosomes the
telomeres become shorter and shorter
so that seems to contribute to the
process of aging
so as you can see here
in a young organism the telomeres are
longer
in an older organism
the telomeres are shorter
and it is also believed that if you
if you are able to prevent the
shortening of the telomeres then you may
actually end up either slowing down or
even stopping
the process of aging and that is where
this all this research is is
being focused right now on on trying to
stop the process of the shortening of
telomeres if you can do that then you
may be able to prevent aging and you may
have
permanent youthful life you know so that
that is uh still a work in progress it's
still far away if it ever happens
but that is how the process of aging
seems to happen yeah so it doesn't have
anything to do with time dilation or
special relativity or general relativity
it's just biology right
that is what is behind the process of
aging
okay runtime says can you explain about
different constellations and their
significance
what are constellations
constellations are various arrangements
of stars that we see in the night sky
so if you go out in the dark people
these days don't look at the sky you go
out into the
go out into the open at night where
there is
less light pollution then you will be
able to see lots of stars in the sky
and if you see the stars
we human beings are very good at
perceiving shapes even when there are
where there are no shapes so in the old
days our ancestors would look at the
stars look at the sky and they would
imagine that the stars come in the the
arrangements of stars
is in various shapes and they would give
names
to these shapes
one of the famous ones in sanskrit is
called the saptarishi constellation in
in english it's called the great bear or
the great or the big dipper or whatever
so let's see what constellations look
like
there are the constellations here we are
so um this is the orion
constellation
orion's belt is there right
it's the is the hunter
and this is a sky chart with various uh
constellations cassiopeia
andromeda
fornax sculptor and so on so forth so
these are the various constellations
uh sagittarius scorpios libra serpents
the snake
capricorn the goat and so on and so
forth right so these are the various
constellations they are simply stars
that we have imagined to to be arranged
in various shapes
and that's how we perceive it from here
if we were to go to a different star
system
then we would see the star from a
different perspective and then you would
have different constellations you would
not find the same constellations from a
different star system if you were to go
to let's say proxima centauri
and look at the sky from there you would
not see the same night sky as what we
see from here on earth
so it's all a question of your
perspective of where you are
where you are located
and you see a certain perspective from
there right
so that's what the constellations are
the various
shapes that we have imagined that the
stars are arranged in
and typically it's the brightest stars
that we arrange in these shapes i mean
that's how we imagine the shapes to
to be
that's what constellations are we call
them
in sanskrit what is their significance
there is no real significance of course
we we find
significance in everything so there is
this entire uh
thing called astrology the zodiac
zodiacal science and
um the constellations are named after
zodiac signs or zodiac signs are the
constellations and it seems to have some
relationship with astrology not
astronomy
and what that is i don't know
i have no understanding or expertise in
this particular field astrology so
so that's all i can tell you
uh
from my perspective the only
significance is that it it it looks like
various shapes and that's what we we
have imagined
there is no physical
significance as such
from my perspective as a scientist i i
don't understand astrology
so that's what i can say
long question
rishabh says do you think we are
creating a prison and trapping ourselves
unknowingly
for future space missions or satellites
stop working after a certain time it
just becomes a rogue uncontrollable
object orbiting the earth
there are lots of satellites orbiting
the earth without any control they're
dead they're dead
if the number keeps increasing rapidly
then it will be impossible for humans in
the future to send rockets to any other
planet
if this becomes reality then what will
be the solution uh it is becoming
increasingly a problem an issue that
needs to be looked into seriously
it's not just dead satellites it's also
space junk
debris you know
uh so that's becoming a problem there is
there is this entire cloud of space
debris around the earth
let me see
space debris what does it look like
so this
is
a representation of the major
such objects that are in orbit around
the earth
these are the major ones but there are
lots more such objects which are you
know centimeters in size that can cause
massive damage to a spacecraft or rocket
they can even
i mean puncture the the walls of a space
station and and cause
well
catastrophic damage
so yeah the space debris is
definitely a big problem so is the
problem of of
drifting boosters in space boosters
typically
re-enter the atmosphere quickly and burn
up or fall into space or fall into
oceans or maybe somewhere else but these
dead satellites etc are and especially
space debris the broken up space debris
is a big problem and if we don't do
something about it now it's going to
like you say trap us in a prison that we
will be on we will be surface bound we
will not be able to safely launch
rockets
if there is so much debris and minimum
you know that could uh prevent
future space exploration so that is
certainly something that could happen in
the future if we don't take steps to
rectify the problem right now so what
steps can we take
the simplest
action that
we can take
is that any satellite that is launched
should have
an expiry date
and it should have a mechanism
that once the expiry date is reached it
re-enters the earth atmosphere and burns
up in the atmosphere so you could
provide it with a small rocket motor
rocket engine or something for simply
for just this purpose but when it
reaches a certain amount of
time in space
it will be
uh brought back into the atmosphere and
allowed to burn up
you do that it's going to solve the
problem but of course
a rocket motor rocket engine
costs money
it also adds extra weight
to the bill that you to the bill that
you to pay when you launch your your
spacecraft so yeah most people
uh most nations most companies most
corporations would try to cut down on
that cost right
and leave the problem for the future so
that is a problem so i think there needs
to be some kind of consensus among the
space-faring nations
that this is the new standard or norm
that we need to uh all follow if we do
that then at least the space these
spacecraft the satellites we are
launching now and in the future
will not contribute further to this
problem right
so yeah that is the one solution i can
think of that ensure that every single
satellite that is launched
is allowed to remain in orbit for a
certain
specific number of years you decide what
the number of years is you want it to be
there for five years great it's your
choice you want to do that for 20 years
your choice but at the end of the time
period it is your responsibility that
you bring it down and make it burn up
into the in the atmosphere so that sort
of thing needs to be done if you do that
then things will be fine
oman says is there any any evidence to
suggest that the laws of physics remain
constant in this universe as assumed by
sir albert einstein in the special
theory of relativity
um
all the evidence that we have
tells us that the laws of physics seem
to be the same no matter where we look
so how do we know this we know this
through observational evidence
the laws of physics that apply to us
over here
on our home planet are the same laws of
physics
that apply anywhere else that are in
force anywhere else in the in the
universe
even if you have a galaxy
that's 10 billion light years away from
here
the same laws of physics are known
to be enforced there as well because we
are able to make observational uh make
observations through telescopes and
other various other instruments and from
all the evidence that we have gathered
over all these past few decades
over the past century and more all of
this evidence has not thrown up a single
instance
of any
known law of physics
being violated right
so everything that we know about physics
is true even they're out in outer space
so thus far we have found no evidence
that suggests
that the laws of physics change
in different directions or or are or
they are different far away from here
all right
so from all the evidence that we have
the laws of physics are the same
everywhere thus far
jasmine says what is the definition of
consciousness in your modern physics if
there is one
considering the fact that physics has
rules and laws and theories for
everything
there is no definition of consciousness
in modern physics
consciousness
we don't know what it is
we don't even have a definition for it
then that's why we are not able to
discuss it or or do research in it
consciousness does
seem to
be a thing in physics
uh it it may or may not have some kind
of role to play
in various interpretations of quantum
mechanics here
so consciousness is
of becoming increasingly important
especially in the frontiers of physics
possibly possibly yeah but we still
don't have a definition of what
consciousness is consciousness as far as
we understand seems to be
possibly a biological phenomenon
we know that we are conscious but we
don't know how to define what this
consciousness is consciousness seems to
be a combination of various
characteristics
we are conscious we know that animals
are conscious our pet doggy or pet cat
they are conscious birds are conscious
we when we see
something that is conscious we recognize
that immediately but
we don't have a clear
scientific definition of consciousness
we have various artistic definitions of
consciousness etcetera but science is a
rigorous thing
it's a rigorous practice and we need
very clear and precise definitions of
phenomena if we want to actually examine
those phenomena and in a scientific
manner and unfortunately we don't have a
definition of consciousness the question
is
what are the characteristics of a
conscious system let's call it a system
let's say i have a box in space
and let's say that box is conscious
what are the characteristics that it
should exhibit
in order to be conscious
is there a con consensus for that
we're talking about a box
not a human being
so what is the difference between a
conscious box and a conscious human
being what's the difference between a
conscious computer if such a thing would
exist ever
and a conscious human being we don't
have any clear
definition of what constitutes
consciousness clearly consciousness has
something to do with memory
without memory there is no consciousness
to be conscious you need to first be
conscious that you exist
to be conscious of yourself you need to
have some memories of the past
so there seems to be some relationship
with memory
so a system that is conscious needs to
be able to store memory to be able to
store memory it needs to have
organs
that capture information from the
outside universe
right so now we are talking about
biological
uh
aspects of that because
or maybe mechanical aspects so
we're not quite able to define clearly
precisely and
unambiguously what a conscious system is
like what are its characteristics you
know sufficient necessary and sufficient
conditions
for something to be conscious so we
don't have that as of today and that's
why it's uh
well now impossible to
have any meaningful discussion of
consciousness in science as of today
maybe in the future things will change
keshav says in one of the recent videos
you have said that the brain can be
developed differently
when you
learn multiple languages
is it about thinking abilities or actual
physical changes that happen in the mind
um there seems to be a relationship
between multilingualism
being multilingual and the iq score that
you uh
that you that you
get when you do an iq test so people who
are multilingual seem to have
a somewhat
higher
intelligence quotient now iq is not
necessarily a measure of your
intelligence some people say it's a
pseudo pseudoscientific swindle or
whatever but there seems to be a
correlation between knowing more than
one language and the amount of iq points
that you have more than the average yeah
that's one thing now
i'm not sure if people if anyone has
done a study of
multilingual people and what sort of
brain structure they have i'm not sure
about that but what we do know is that
there was a study that was done
um
in people
who memorized large
large quantities of sanskrit texts
so uh
let me see if i have any of that here
i think it's called the sanskrit effect
right
so
so there are these scholars pundits who
memorize entire
large
large sanskrit texts they memorize it
precisely not just the text itself but
the correct pronunciation
in the way in which you're supposed to
recite it and all that and they do it
for years and years and years and what
was
discovered
is that
certain portions of their brain are more
developed than others now we don't know
if it is only something to do with
sanskrit only or other languages also if
you memorize things
will it have the same effect but thus
far it seems to be
uh isolated to only sanskrit as far as
we know it's called the sanskrit effect
let me show you what this looks like
um
let me pull that up on the screen give
me a second please
there was this article in scientific
american
yeah it's called a neuroscientist
explores the sanskrit effect mri scans
show that memorizing ancient mantras
increases the size of brain regions
associated with cognitive
function
and yeah this article describes all of
that
um so these these vedic sanskrit pundits
that train for years to orally memorize
and exactly recite
very ancient texts which are 40 000 to
100 000 words right
they discovered that the structural mri
scanning was remarkable
numerous regions in the brains of the
pundits were dramatically larger than
those of other people with with over 10
percent more gray matter across both
cerebral hemispheres and substantial
increases in cortical thicknesses and so
on so forth
and
more interestingly for verbal memory
the pundit's right hippocampus a region
of the brain that plays a vital role in
short as well as long-term memory had
more grey matter
across nearly 75 percent of this
subcortical structure
and so on and so forth so yes
the memorization of sanskrit texts
seems to alter
the structure of your brain and thicken
certain regions and
it's certainly
something that is detectable in mri
scans
so yeah that is what i can tell you
about being multilingual and whether
that has an effect on the brain
structure we i am not quite sure maybe
you can do your own research and find
out if any such study has been done but
this is what i know for sure
okay
next question
avinash says if a distant solar system
is millions of light years away
and so we see it as it was millions of
years ago how can we see what it looks
like now
we can't
we cannot
in relativity simultaneity itself
doesn't exist
whether two events happen simultaneously
or not depends on where you are relative
to these two events if you are in a
certain position location and space time
the two events may appear to happen
simultaneously from your perspective
but your friend who may be in certain
other police position in space time may
see one event happen before the other so
this is called the simultaneity of
relativity this is something you learn
when you study special relativity
so simultaneous events are not
necessarily simultaneous they are
simultaneous only for certain people in
certain places and for certain observers
now
if you you have a solar system that's a
million light years away
you're seeing it right now through the
telescope or whatever
you're seeing what happened there a
million years ago
let's say you receive a message
from an alien
civilization
yeah and you try to figure out where it
came from and you see that it it came
from a system that is a million light
years away
then
what happened actually is that those
people
who sent you that message message
sent that message a million years before
today
right so that's how it is there is no
way of there is no such thing as right
now right now happens only here
what is right now here is not right now
there
simultaneity itself
is not quite a thing
in physics in in special relativity yeah
so you can never see
what it looks like right now
you can only see what it looked like
then that's just how it is there is no
way around
this uh
restriction so to say
quotes quotes says
what time is it at the polls north pole
and south pole
okay let's see what the polls look like
shall we ah we're gonna bring in the map
today
in a
science session
uh sorry not this one
let me bring in something else let me
bring in the map
where's the map here's the map okay
poles
so
on the top of the north pole on the
bottom you have the south pole
let's say you are sitting you are
standing at the north pole
and you go
10 kilometers south
10 kilometers west
and then again 10 kilometers north you
will end up again at the north pole
right so that's how it is so
no matter which direction you go in
south
and if you if you do this procedure you
will end up at the north pole and
similarly the reverse happens at the
south pole
so the earth has these
longitudes
which give us the time zones
but the thing is at the poles all the
longitudes converge
right
all the longitudes
converge at the poles
which means that if you are at the poles
you can decide whatever time it is it is
it is all times at once time doesn't
really have a meaning
from the perspective of time zones at
the polls
so let's say you are from india
and you're working in antarctica you go
to the south pole
you can decide that it is indian
standard time over there
but your friend who is from chile
can say that it is a chilean standard
time over there
and another friend of yours who is from
south africa could say that it is south
african standard time
so it doesn't matter
at the polls you can
interpret it as whatever time you want
it to be because all the
longitudes converge
at the poles
so all times are the same at the poles
curran says what are
microbial black holes
microbial black holes so i have never
heard of
i
i've never heard of microbial black
holes i i know about microscopic black
holes
microbes which is microscopic organisms
are indeed
microbial microscopic
but they're not black holes and black
holes are
not living organisms
right so there is no such thing as a
microbial black hole but there are
possibly
microscopic black holes
mbh
and
microscopic black holes could have been
produced in in incredible numbers
enormous quantities
in the very early universe
during the reheating period even before
inflation before the inflationary epoch
during the inflationary epoch as well
possibly yeah an overproduction of
microscopic black holes could have
happened during these various
phases of the very early history of our
universe because of quantum fluctuations
and these fluctuations creating regions
very small regions of over density that
would collapse into a singularity into a
black hole and that sort of thing so
these are the hypothetical microscopic
black holes that we have never observed
thus far but they can exist from
the law according to the laws of physics
such black holes can certainly be formed
so that is microscopic black holes if
they formed in the very early universe
they would be called they would also be
called primordial black holes
so that's what it is it's not microbial
but microscopic
black holes
okay down to earth says the question is
about poison
poison
if poison reaches expiry date will it
get more or less poisonous
poison and expiry dates you know
there's a funny thing that you see
sometimes you go to a supermarket you
want to buy himalayan pink salt
so you will get
a box a tin whatever of himalayan pink
salt
on the label it will say this is pure
himalayan pink salt it is more than 200
million years old
more than 200 million years old and then
it will say expiry within six months of
manufacture
does it make any sense something has
been around for 200 million years but
it's going to expire in the next six
months or next 12 months
so
what i'm trying to say is that very
often these expiry dates have no meaning
when you produce a food product or some
other product
sometimes or often times
by law
you are required to give a specific
expiry date
but that expiry date may just may
sometimes just just be for the sake for
namesake you know
uh
i remember reading a long time ago some
time ago that uh scientists discovered
ancient medications from the 1940s etc
you know strips of tablets and all that
and they tested them for efficacy and
obviously they had expired decades ago
but they were found to work just fine
even though they had officially expired
so very often these expiry dates don't
mean a lot of mean a lot yeah
now obviously i am talking about food
products and medicines not poisons
so it depends i would say
certain
poisons are chemicals essentially yeah
certain chemicals
uh
have a certain amount of stability and
if they come into contact with moisture
for instance
or or heat they may degrade and their
chemical composition will def
may change possibly or their efficacy
potency may decrease over time so it
depends
so i don't know
if all poisons will become less
poisonous after expiry date or even if
poisons do have expirations i'm not sure
right
potassium cyanide is one of the scariest
poisons we know of right one of the most
infamous poisons potassium cyanide does
it have
an expiration date it's just kcn right
the chemical compound i don't think it
expires but does it but does it react
with it with with moisture
maybe it does maybe it doesn't i'm not
quite sure i'm not quite proficient with
in chemistry and all that
i would say that poisons would
eventually depending on what they're
made of
would over time reduce
lose some of its potency let's say you
have rat poison
or we spoke about cockroaches cockroach
poison
uh
if you open the wrapper or whatever it
comes in and you leave it open for a
month maybe it may not work after a
month maybe
so typically over time the efficacy
would decrease but in some cases it may
also not we don't know
so yeah it depends on what it is made up
of
and
more or less some of its efficacy
efficacy
may decrease possibly
all right that's about poisons i think i
will now take
some
live chat questions for a few minutes
all right
do we have any live chat questions if
you have any
shoot away
okay people ask me questions about
history about geopolitics about current
affairs
today is science
you have questions about science go for
it
okay let's someone is saying
okay i'm not getting any science
questions i'm getting all kinds of other
questions so the saddam hussein chinese
pie ship 24 election
why have you stopped taking live
questions i just took a life question
sir
ask me a question about science
how do we sleep and there's a question
this is a
there's a representation of a sleeping
person here see let's see where is it
here here
uh how do we sleep we sleep with our
with our eyes closed and uh
we fall out of consciousness
and we enter zone zone or a state of
altered consciousness which means that
we are not aware of our surroundings
but there's something else going on in
our minds we call it dreaming
and most often most like in most cases
we
tend to forget what we were dreaming we
do remember we had an interesting dream
and we wish we could remember it but
mostly
in most cases we forget our dreams after
we wake up within within seconds
typically of waking up unless the moment
you wake up you you put your mind on
that what you're dreaming about
so
that is sleep it is a state of altered
consciousness of unconsciousness
essentially
and there is this phase of rem sleep
rapid eye movement sleep and there are
various kinds of brain waves associated
with different phases of sleep there are
sleep cycles i think it's 90 minute
cycles in which you have a complete
sleep cycle and so on
um it's not very well understood why we
need sleep and so on maybe we are
consolidating the memories that we form
during the daytime maybe the brain
needs of cerebral spinal spinal fluid
baths
to take over the impurities or whatever
else
and if you don't sleep enough you may
you have the formation of a myeloid
plaque in the brain
you may be more susceptible to dementia
and to alzheimer's disease etc these are
the things about sleep uh how do we
sleep that's how you sleep
go lie down close your eyes and
eventually we'll drift off to sleep if
the time is right that's how it happens
okay
anything else
uh
what are the implications what
implications would be the existence of
the line of evil
in the cosmic microwave background
what kind of the possible uses of
antimatter provided we can store it i
have never heard of any line of evil in
the cosmic microwave background
never heard of it
so yeah i don't know that
uses of antimatter you could use
antimatter to produce produce energy
you take a bunch of antimatter you you
mix it with
regular matter it will immediately
annihilate itself and give off pure
energy in the form of mostly i would
imagine photons yeah
and heat and all that and you could
harness that to produce
for propulsion for for like a nuclear
reactor for instance
you could use it for weaponry
and so on so forth yeah so it is
it could give you pure energy which you
could use in any way or shape or form
that you want
if you can store it that is the major
problem the number one problem is how to
how to make antimatter it's very very
very very very hard to make antimatter
it's the most expensive substance you
can imagine
and secondly how to store it because
it's very hard to store it
right
and again people are asking me questions
not related to science i don't
understand why they do this
how did life start on start on earth
it's a major massive mystery
a biogenesis
right
so
we don't know but it is believed that
because of the conditions of the very
early
planet
a lot of lightning and the mixture of
gases that you had
and very wet
environment
and this entire
mixture of of factors this combination
of factors
conspired
to brew
amino acids that became the precursors
of proteins and then somehow this
mysterious
molecule called dna appeared from
somewhere and then all of this mixed
together to form the first life that's
what is thought that's what's believed
but we don't quite know for sure how it
happened
this theory is called a biogenesis the
the emergence of life from non-living
matter
okay do we have anything else
do we have anything else
i've taken many of these questions
multiple times
yeah i guess that's it then for now we
have crossed two hours so i'm gonna end
it here
thank you very much for all the
questions i know there are lots of other
questions we'll keep taking them and
please look at my older videos and
and
many of the questions you're asking me
have already been answered but anyway
i'm happy to keep answering your
questions keep keep the questions coming
and we will keep answering them but for
today we are done
so i will see you in the next episode
until then take care
and
bye